<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Good newes for Christendome Sent to a Venetian in Ligorne, from a merchant in Alexandria. Discouering a wonderfull and strange apparition, visibly seene for many dayes togither in Arabia, ouer the place, where the supposed tombe of Mahomet (the Turkish prophet) is inclosed: by which the learned Arabians prognosticate the reducing &amp; calling of the great Turke to Christianitie. With many other notable accidents: but the most remarkable is the miraculous rayning of bloud about Rome. Done out of the Italian.</title>
            <author>Cortano, Ludovico.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1620</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 57 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 25 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A73765</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 5796.3</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S115623</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99850841</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99850841</idno>
            <idno type="VID">177839</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A73765)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 177839)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 2023:3, 1232:04, 647:05)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Good newes for Christendome Sent to a Venetian in Ligorne, from a merchant in Alexandria. Discouering a wonderfull and strange apparition, visibly seene for many dayes togither in Arabia, ouer the place, where the supposed tombe of Mahomet (the Turkish prophet) is inclosed: by which the learned Arabians prognosticate the reducing &amp; calling of the great Turke to Christianitie. With many other notable accidents: but the most remarkable is the miraculous rayning of bloud about Rome. Done out of the Italian.</title>
                  <author>Cortano, Ludovico.</author>
                  <author>Butter, Nathaniel, d. 1664, attributed name.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 40 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed [by G. Purslowe] for Nathaniel Butter,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1620.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Woodcut title vignette.</note>
                  <note>Possibly translated by Nathaniel Butter.</note>
                  <note>Page 36 signed: Ludouico Cortano.</note>
                  <note>B1r has headpiece of type ornaments. B3r catchword: acquaintance,.</note>
                  <note>Gatherings B and D in different setting of type than first edition (STC 5796).</note>
                  <note>Identified as STC 5796a on UMI microfilm reel 647 and STC 5796 on UMI microfilm reel 1232.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect; the British Library copy catalogued is imperfect; title page trimmed affecting text.</note>
                  <note>Reproductions of the originals in the Folger Shakespeare Library, the British Library, and the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Curiosities and wonders --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Miracles (Islam) --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:177839:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:177839:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:177839:2"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Good Newes to Chriſtendome.</hi> Sent to a Venetian in Ligorne, from a Merchant in ALEXANDRIA. Diſcouering a wonderfull and ſtrange Apparition, viſibly ſeene for many dayes togither in Arabia, ouer the place, where the ſuppoſed Tombe of MAHOMET (the Turkiſh Prophet) is incloſed: By which the learned Arabians prognoſticate the Reducing &amp; Calling of the great Turke to Chriſtianitie. With many other notable Accidents: But the moſt remarkable is the miraculous rayning of Bloud about ROME. <hi>Done out of the Italian.</hi>
            </p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>depiction of fire raining down on a city from a cloud carrying an army of soldiers and horses, including one holding a flag with a crescent; beside the city, a large group, some with scimitars and some with arms raised, look up to the cloud; in the top right corner, a female figure holding a sword and book, and enclosed in the sun, looks on</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>LONDON, Printed for NATHANIEL BVTTER. 1620.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:177839:3"/>
         </div>
         <div type="translator_to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:177839:3"/>
            <head>THE TRANSLATOR to the Reader.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Gentle Reader:</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>
               </hi> Confeſſe vnto you, when this let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter came first into my hand; which was about the 20 of <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cember,</hi> brought as it ſhould ſeeme by ſome of the last <hi>Vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian</hi> company, I read it as a thing according to the Italian phraſe, <hi>trouata</hi> or <hi>bugiarda;</hi> and chriſtned it with this opinion, that it could march in no other rancke of veritie, then amongst our ſelues the <hi>Suſſex Serpent,</hi> the <hi>German Ghoſts,</hi> and the great Armie met in <hi>Tar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tarie</hi> marching by the <hi>Caſpian</hi> ſhore ouer <hi>Taurus,</hi> all which of my owne knowledge came out of the ſhop of invention, and were beholding more to deuiſe, then ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther religion or diſcretion: ſo that in a manner I diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claimed the tranſlating of it, and put it from me with a kinde of contracted brow: but in truth there were cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine
<pb facs="tcp:177839:4"/> reaſons, which got the maſterie ouer my Iudgment, and kept that a while predominant againſt further pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption. Firſt, the difficultie of the ſtile, being my ſelf a very poore Linguiſt. For had not the pulling hooke of <hi>Florios</hi> Dictionarie brought many words neerer vnto me, they had all paſſed for ſtrangers, and thoſe which you haue, meerely come from the apprehenſion of the ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence in the coherence of the matter, rather then the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular ſignification of the words by themſelues. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, the time, wherein we liue, not like that conciſe Hiſtoriographer <hi>Cornelius Tacitus,</hi> who ſpake what he thought, and wrote what he ſpake; but we as ſoldiers vnder good Commanders, who must ſimply obey, and though neuer ſo wiſe, diſpute not a word by way of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtation with the buſines impoſed. Thirdly, a priuate conference with ſome <hi>Italians,</hi> who only put it off with a ſhrug of the ſhoulder, when any thing is diſtasting vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them: although ſome of them went further, and cryed out aloud, as their manner is, <hi>Cancro</hi> and <hi>Cazzo</hi> when they diſlike a thing. Laſt of all, my owne poore affaires, which haue buſied me otherwiſe, and out of the rules of moralitie tyed me to the preuention of wants, and that intolerable and inſupportable vexation to depend vpon any mans bountie. For queſtionles Friendſhip now adaies is but like a fire from a painted cloth, which for all the braue ſhow reflecteth no warmth: ſo that I may
<pb facs="tcp:177839:4"/> well conclude with the Dutchman, he neuer fared worſe then when he wiſht for his dinner: notwithſtanding all theſe reaſons, and ſome thing elſe more pleaſantly enfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, the importunitie of my freinds, and that ſame <hi>auri ſacra fames,</hi> got the vpper hand of nicitie, and not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly put the booke into my hand, but extracted this poore revolution out of a barren ſpring, which more and more I confeſſe opened her ſelfe from my owne affection to the matter and poore experience of certaine repinings euen amongst the <hi>Turks</hi> themſelues, against the long pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traction of <hi>Mahomets</hi> returne, being now full 40 yeere elapſed beyond their owne account, and his promiſe to bring them glad tidings of a new Paradice: and in truth when I conſidered thoſe excellent praedictions of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, that Antichrist ſhall not only be diſcouered, but euen puniſhed in this world; that the Iewes ſhould be recalled, and all apparantly to be ſeene before that doome of doomes, and ſcourge of incredulitie, the terror of the last iudgement, I caſt vp a new account for the entertaining this relation, and rancked it thus in the maniple of my endeuors, which though it troupe with a file or two, yet according to the ſtraitnes of the paſſage may ſerue the turne, as well as a greater Armie, or ſtronger forces. Accept it then, good Reader, and if you be not curious concerning the fullnes of truth, and infallibilitie of the matter; you may make this bulruſh of noueltie hold vp
<pb facs="tcp:177839:5"/> your head in the calmer waters of ſecuritie, that you ſink not ouer head and eares into pride, contempt, and care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſnes. Firſt, conſidering God hath ſuch a worke to bring to paſſe, and he will finiſh it in his due time. Secondly, that although the <hi>Vrim</hi> and the <hi>Thummim</hi> ceaſe, and miracles are very ſparing; yet the heauens declare the glory of God, and many fearefull accidents haue bin prefigured by apparition. Thirdly, that therefore the heauens burne firſt to light vs the way to repentance, and ſeeing there muſt come a diſſolution of all things, to prepare our hearts to put confidence in nothing: Fourth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and that we be not ſo ſtupefied, as not to admire the <hi>Apocalyps</hi> of hidden mysteries, but verily belieue there is ſomething to be done, which we cannot apprehend by reaſon. Laſt of all, to continue our holy duties, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally priuate prayers, and contrition, which ſhall ſo molli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie our hard hearts, that they ſhall make the lifting vp of our hands as incenſe, and by way of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitiation moue God to continue his mercies, and auert his iudgments from vs.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="account">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:177839:5"/>
            <head>TO THE MAGNIFI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CENT SIGNIOR ALUISO CANDIDO, of the familie of Mori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſini, reſident at LEGORNE, as Gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor of the Venetian Factorie there.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Right worthy:</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Ccording to the truſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed in me, I made my commorance in <hi>Allex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>andria,</hi> all the while the goods were vnloding out of the <hi>Caſtor</hi> &amp; <hi>Pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lux</hi> of <hi>Leuca:</hi> wherein I receiued thoſe balles of ſilke, and roules of gold, for which I preſently trucked with <hi>Eleazar Bedly</hi> the <hi>Iew,</hi> dwelling in
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:177839:6"/> the <hi>Semiter</hi> ſtreete of the tribe of <hi>Iſachar,</hi> and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued in <hi>ſultaneſes</hi> and vncut ſtones, what I thought correſpondent to the value, all which I haue returned vnto you by my booke of ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts, vnder the truſt of <hi>Bartholomeo Ioco</hi> the <hi>Florentine,</hi> who ſtandeth charged &amp; is accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table for the ſame: the greater ſtuffs and cheſts of glaſſes are entred into the blancks of the cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome-houſe, and you ſhall receiue the bill of <hi>Beniamin Hely</hi> the <hi>Iew,</hi> who is chiefe farmer vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the <hi>Baſhâ</hi> for the ſame: and ſo when I had thus ordered your buſineſſe with ſome cheere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full confidence, that you ſhould receiue 4. for one; I tooke the opportunitie of a <hi>Turkiſh Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſall,</hi> and went preſently to <hi>Cayro:</hi> we tooke the middle ſtreame: for you muſt know, that <hi>Nilus</hi> brancheth out with 7. heads into the midland ſea, &amp; hauing a pleaſant wind North<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weſt and by north, quickly ſaluted the riuer in her fulneſſe, which without controuerſie had driuen vs backe with the ſwiftneſſe of his cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent, had not the goodneſſe of our ſailes coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terchecked the violence of his ſpeede, ſo that we made three daies iorney of this paſsage and although I doe not accuſtome to fill vp a pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate letter with publike diſcourſes, either con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:177839:6"/> 
               <hi>Topography</hi> or <hi>Poligraphy,</hi> yet cannot I o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer paſſe an accident that happened vnto vs the ſecond day: For a little a fore noone we heard a great cry among the reedes, and wondring what it was, we might well perceiue it was no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but a crocadile howling ouer a woman, whom it had caught? as if a heard of wolues had bin comming downe the mountaine to barke at the moone. And truly <hi>Good Sir,</hi> it is ſtrange to relate, how rauenous and fell in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires theſe creatures are of women, and will hunt them extreamely by the ſent, imitating the <hi>Allegators</hi> of <hi>Guinea,</hi> neuer to ſhow their bodies till they can obteine their pray: yea ſuch is their manner, that they will paſſe by children and men, and take onely the oportunitie to ſurpriſe the women, whom they will ſtrip as hanſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of their apparell, after they haue brought them to their neſts, as if they had bin taught a kind of cunning not to be combred with their ſluttiſhneſs: yet muſt I not let paſse this ſecret of nature, that they commonly vſe to pinch the necke and head ſo at the firſt, that the miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable wretch left to a pray findeth a curteſie in the diſpatch of her life, for otherwiſe it were a thouſand deaths to be ſo long a dying, conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:177839:7"/> ſhe is three howres a howling ouer the body, before ſhe deuoure it, of which yet how rauenous ſo euer ſhe be, ſhe leaues the head on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly vntouched, but after ſhe hath done howling, ſhe eates, after eating ſhe weepes, after weeping ſhe ſleepes, &amp; then, they are many times ſlaine, and their young ones ſtolne from them: this was the voice we heard, and within an hower after we met a boat of <hi>Aegiptians,</hi> who came to ſeeke the woman, and diſcouered vnto vs, that ſhe was a poore mans wife, that had beene to gather reedes that morning with her husband, and by reaſon of ſome diſpleaſure, thought to be reuenged by ſequeſtring her ſelfe, and ſo was ſurpriſed by the ſerpent, as a warning to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther women, not to make euery ſmall vnkind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, the author of a lumpiſh countenance, or a ſullen heart: the next day we aproached the great Citie, of which to talke neuer ſo little, would make my letter to great, and beſides you haue bin in theſe parts your ſelfe, &amp; make dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly vſe of moſt <hi>vberant</hi> relations, &amp; remarkable circumſtances. It was not long ere I prepared my lodging, nor long ere <hi>Signior Stephano Del<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phino</hi> came vnto me, who finding more conue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niency in mine then his owne, quickly ſetled
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:177839:7"/> himſelfe to beare me company, nor long ere the great <hi>Carauan</hi> troup of marchants ariued from <hi>Ormus,</hi> who came the next way ouer <hi>Ara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bia</hi> with 600. Camels, and 200. <hi>Arabian</hi> horſe for their <hi>Conuoy,</hi> whoſe intertainement for 5. weekes coſt the Merchants 3000. <hi>Checkinoes</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them: they onely taried a day and a night to make themſelues drunke; which they may quickly doe. For though the wine of <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſtina,</hi> which we much vented here, be reaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble good, yet as if they would pleaſure <hi>Bacchus</hi> with an vnſatiate deſire to cellebrate his <hi>Orgies,</hi> they intermingled the berries of <hi>Aethiopia,</hi> whoſe fulſome iuyce doe rather intoxicate the braine, then quench the thirſt: The next day they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted, and the next day I ſingled out the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panie, to finde what <hi>Italians</hi> were amongſt them: For in a word I neuer ſaw ſo many ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers in one iourney and agreeing ſo well toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, the report of it was pleaſant, but when I heard it from their owne mouthes, it added both delight &amp; conte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, I could both name the parties and the places of their aboad. But becauſe I aime at another marke I will not vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>furniſh my quiuer to ſpend a rouing ſhaft to no purpoſe, but in a word, here were many of my
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:177839:8"/> acquaintance, amongſt whome only <hi>Siluano Gritti</hi> and <hi>Bartholomeo Caponi</hi> with two friers, one an <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> another of the order of <hi>Serui,</hi> lodged in the ſame houſe with vs: They ſpent three daies in reſt, and reſted the night very ſoundly, yet the friers were many times iang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, and ſo angred <hi>Signior Stephano,</hi> that ouer-paſſionate one night he bad the deuill take them, whether they croſſed themſelues or no: the darkneſs interdicted my diſcouerie, but I will be ſworne, I heard them thump their breaſts to my bed, and I intreated my <hi>Gent:</hi> to let them alone. Oh, ſaid the <hi>Mendicant</hi> frier, lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle do you know the diſceptation betweene vs, and leſſe may we inſtruct you in it, till a fitter opportunity. For we haue ſuch a ſtrange ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to diſcourſe vpon, as will ſpend a day in the <hi>Epitome,</hi> and make all <hi>Europe</hi> to wonder in the exemplification.</p>
            <p>Truly good <hi>Sir,</hi> the very <hi>Emphaſis</hi> of his words amaſed me, and the ouer deſire of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction led me preſently to the way of vigi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancy, and I ſat vp in my bed, as if I meant to heare a tale indeede, had not <hi>Signior Stephano</hi> made me alſo the ſubiect of his anger, and bad me go out of the bed, if I was ſo womaniſh and
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:177839:8"/> idle, that I could not tarry til day light, to heare a lying tale of a frier.</p>
            <p>Till this the <hi>Auguſtine</hi> frier was ſilent, but now in ſome diſtemperature raiſed his <hi>paſsion,</hi> as high as euer <hi>Signior Stephanoes</hi> was, telling him to his face, it was ſpoke like a <hi>Lutherane,</hi> and <hi>Heretick,</hi> to lay any ſuch imputation on men of their qualitie, religious obſeruants, and father-confeſſors. For they made a conſcience of tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling an vntruth, and acknowledged it more then a <hi>Veniall</hi> ſin to countenance a lie through the credit of any religious order: well; ſaid <hi>Sig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nior Stephano</hi> if you will not lie in your words, yet I pray you lie ſtill in your beds, and it ſhall be part of my penance, to acknowledge mine error, and make a retractation of offending you: This anſwere made way to the ſedation of this vnquietneſſe, and ſo we gaue ouer our parlee, and made ſome vſe of a mornings ſleepe.</p>
            <p>The next day the friers of themſelues remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bring their <hi>Matutine</hi> howers, after deuotion was ouerpaſſed, came voluntarilie into our chamber, and with a ſmall preamble of pacifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation preuailed ſo much with my compani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, (who by this time was as deſirous of the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:177839:9"/> 
               <hi>nouelty,</hi> as my ſelfe) that we aroſe, and becauſe they would not bee interrupted in their diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, we made a ſhort repaſt together, and ſo locking the dore to vs, attended the poore <hi>Men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicant;</hi> who thus began.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>My</hi> Brother and <hi>I about the tenth of September,</hi> embarked our ſelues from <hi>Ormus,</hi> and came to <hi>Catara,</hi> where the <hi>Chriſtian Carauan</hi> was almoſt ready for their voyage to <hi>Cayro,</hi> but before I proceed any further, I will be plaine to tell you the occaſion of our going thither; 1. partly for Curioſity; 2. partly for Deuotion; 3. partly for Wealth.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Firſt, for curioſity, the deſire of acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taince with forraigne Countries, and the wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingneſſe to put the <hi>Practique</hi> in the other ſcale againſt the <hi>Theory;</hi> or, if you pleaſe, to make our ſuperficiall reading the ſweeter by induſtrious experience, taught vs the way to conceiue, that all Countries might be nationall to a wiſe man.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Secondly, concerning Deuotion, hauing long ſince heard, that the <hi>Perſians</hi> in this place condiſcended euen againſt the rule of their <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>choran,</hi> to communicate with certaine <hi>Portingall</hi> Friers, about the <hi>Verity</hi> of both Religions, wee
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:177839:9"/> thought it not amiſſe to put it to the triall, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther we might attaine to ſuch a meritorious act as the <hi>Conuerſion of a Mahumetane.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. Thirdly, concerning Wealth, at the end of <hi>Auguſt</hi> there is a generall fiſhing for Pearle, by reaſon that the <hi>Oyſters</hi> in this hot moneth re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſort to the ſhore, and as if nature had taught them to breathe for aire, they gape, as it were in ſholes, and then the fiſhers, and ſuch as are appointed for this purpoſe, throw little peble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtones into their mouthes, and ſo keepe them from cloſing againe; and thus are their Pearles kindly taken out, and knowne to be full ripe by their colour. For you muſt conſider the Pearles growe as the meat in bignes, and yeeld great plentie being ſoft, but afterwards moſt worth of eſtimation, as ſhe is <hi>Orientall,</hi> the ſhell makes that we call <hi>Mother of Pearle,</hi> and in the ſame they are ranked together like teeth in ones mouth, as if they were couched in a bed of purpoſe; ſometimes 15. or 16. in a ſhell, onely the <hi>Vnion</hi> hath his name of being alone, and I thinke is priuiledged with extraordinary great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe by being alone: Now at euery draught (or if you will, courſe of ſeparation) they haue a cuſtome by way of gratuitie, to giue to ſuch
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:177839:10"/> religious men as are reſident amongſt them, to ſome more, ſomeleſſe, according as affection ſhall induce them, ſo that for my part ſuch as they are, I haue 500. to ſhew you: at <hi>Catara</hi> we had diuers camels, that came from <hi>Iafu</hi> and <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiffa:</hi> and within three daies according to their cuſtome 200. <hi>Arabian</hi> horſse came from <hi>Zoar</hi> and <hi>Cazape:</hi> there was one principall <hi>Aga</hi> and 4. vnder <hi>Captaines,</hi> and ſo in ſeuerall companies we prepared for the great deſert of <hi>Elact,</hi> paſſing ſuch mountaines and ſtrange woods, that the voiage alone were worthy the deſcription; in regard we found ſnow in greater aboundance, then is in mount <hi>Seneſe,</hi> &amp; ſo many wild beaſts both on the mountaines, and in the woodes, that we lay not one night without a hedge of fier, &amp; in ſeuerall companies we made a ſhow as it were of a burning campe, and both Lions and Tigers came to ſee, what we did, though they durſt not approach, we made thirty daies of this trauell, and ere we came to <hi>Mecha</hi> had only ſight of 3. Townes, for whoſe ſake we fetched a great compaſs, although the pretence was to auoide the hugeſt hills, and ſo we went from <hi>Catara</hi> to <hi>Lagana</hi> to <hi>Salata</hi> and <hi>Gacha:</hi> from thence loding our camells with many skinnes
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:177839:10"/> and teeth of beaſts, as we vnloded them of our prouiſion, we came in good time to <hi>Mecha.</hi> I cannot call it a city becauſe it is vnwalled, nor a village, becauſe it hath 8000. houſes in it, nor rich becauſe the opulent merchant lies at <hi>Liden</hi> a port towne vpon the red ſea, ſome 50. <hi>Italian</hi> mile from <hi>Mecha,</hi> nor poore becauſe it is ſo po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulous, for the reſort of ſo many thouſand ſtrangers that come hither to view the tombe of <hi>Mahomet,</hi> in which (as I my ſelfe was) they are all deceiued: for although he was borne heere, and hath <hi>Charactered</hi> with his <hi>Fame</hi> one of the gloriouſeſt ſtories in the world, yet was he not buried heere, but by a ſtrange policie tranſlated ouer a great deſert, to <hi>Medina Talnabi,</hi> where at this hower is both his Temple and his Sepulcher; by the way you come to the pretty towne of <hi>Tacine:</hi> &amp; howſoeuer any man preſumes of his own cunning, &amp; better intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence, yet from what coaſt ſoeuer he comes, he muſt go to <hi>Mecha</hi> firſt, and their receiue a ticket from the <hi>Beglerbeag;</hi> for which he paies halfe a florence ducket, ere he can be admitted into the <hi>Conuoy</hi> for <hi>Medina:</hi> a littell apprehenſion brought vs to the knowledge of theſe things, and ſo by generall conſent, my brother and I
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:177839:11"/> to cure our vnderſtanding the better, which was almoſt vlcerated with ſtra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge variety both of report and hiſtorie, went thither in perſon about the end of <hi>September,</hi> to be beholding to our owne experience againſt opinion: But be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we came thither, we met with many paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſengers, as it were diſtracted with feare, and when we came found all the country confoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded at a <hi>viſion</hi> or <hi>apparition,</hi> which had laſted for a fortnight, and ſo continuing: 7. daies longer, affrightted the people, and the rather becauſe no man durſt interpret the ſame, or could in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deede be beholding to diſcouery for the truth; only one of the <hi>Deruices,</hi> aſtoniſhed them with a ſudden boldneſſe, and becauſe heere were ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of the race of <hi>Mahomet,</hi> and ſome <hi>Doctors</hi> of the law, who repugning the oratory, rather be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeued <hi>Naturalls</hi> and <hi>Lunaticks,</hi> whom indeede they immagine extraordinarily inſpired with a <hi>Supernaturall Spirit.</hi> the poore <hi>Preeſt</hi> was much offenſiue in his diſcourſe to them all; ſo they conſpired againſt him, and put him to death, by which occaſion heere are Foure remarka<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble things to be conſidered, 1. Firſt the <hi>viſion</hi> it ſelfe. 2. Secondly his <hi>oration,</hi> 3. Thirdly the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of his execution. 4. Fourthly what a <hi>Der<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice</hi> is.</p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:177839:11"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Concerning</hi> the <hi>viſion</hi> about the 20. of <hi>Septem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber,</hi> there happened ſo great a tempeſt, that there was as it were a ſencible darkneſſe about mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>night, ſo fearefull a thunder, that thoſe, which were aſleepe were a wakened at the ſame, and thoſe which were awake, beſides themſelues: at laſt a voice like lightning made a ſtrange rup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and with <hi>Significant Arabian Characters</hi> ſo o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened the thicke cloudes, and diſpelled the va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>powres that with a kinde of ſtench, &amp; ſuffoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting ſmoke the darknes departed, &amp; the people heard, and the reſt read it to this purpoſe, <hi>O why will yee beleeue in lies?</hi> For when the ſtorme was appeaſed, and that the ſerene ellement preſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted herſelfe to their veiwe, they might eaſily read theſe words in the firmament. Some two howres after betweene to and three in the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, there <hi>appeared</hi> a woman all in white com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſed with the beames of the <hi>Sunne,</hi> her counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance was amiable and cheerefull, and ſhe held in her hand a written booke: ſhe had no ſoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner mounted out of the <hi>North weſt</hi> and by <hi>Weſt,</hi> to her full height and radiance, but round a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the <hi>Eaſt,</hi> and <hi>Sowth</hi> many armies of <hi>Turkes, Perſians, Arabians, Moores</hi> and ſuch like appeared, rancked as it were with martiall diſcipline, and
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:177839:12"/> ready to charge vpon her, but ſhee with an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daunted courage, kept her ſtanding, and vſed no other meanes, but only opened the booke, at the ſight whereof the whole army fled, and preſently all the lamps about <hi>Mahomets</hi> tombe were extinguiſhed. For as ſoone as euer the <hi>appariſion</hi> or <hi>viſion vaniſhed,</hi> which was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly an hower before <hi>Sunne</hi> riſing, a pleaſant murmuring wind was heard, to whoſe erupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on they imputed the putting out of the lampes. For you muſt vnderſtand, that though the windowes of the temple, were dooble barrd with iron, and richly guilt, well glazed and cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly cemented, yet the ſtorme came vpon them with ſuch impetuoſitie, that neither glaſſ nor iron withſtood the violence: the Temple, itſelfe is verie high, made with a <hi>rotunde and cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be faſhion,</hi> it hath manie galleries, yet none ſo neere in approch, as to diſcouer, how the Tombe is faſtned: only the common opinion is, that it is made of ſteele, and by cunning <hi>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſture</hi> placed in the <hi>Center</hi> of the Church, vnder a great <hi>Adamant,</hi> whoſe vertue attracted it to the top, this the lamps ſhew plainely, that ther hangs ſuch a coffin: For 3000. lampes continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally, night and day make a moſt reſplendant
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:177839:12"/> ſhow about the galleries, but yet how the cof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fin is faſtned, doe not diſcouer: onely my bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and I learnt thus much, that the coffin is indeede moſt cunningly mortiſed into the roofe, and hath nothing in it, but the firſt <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheron</hi> originally writ by <hi>Sergius</hi> a monck, of the firſt order that euer was, which contracted with him; who liued to ſee the people appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend, that the Angells had drawne him to hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, and kept his monument with their conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuall guard about it: The monck indeed bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried the body iuſt vnder the place, and liued ſo long, that he ſaw this poſition of the religion ratefied, that it was <hi>Capitall</hi> for any man to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute of the veritie of the ſtorie:</p>
            <p>The ancient pilgrims I meane <hi>Turks</hi> of <hi>Maho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mets</hi> race, who after they haue viſited this place neuer cut their haire, were much exanima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and ſo exaſperated at this accident, that they wrecked their anger vpon the poore <hi>Prieſt,</hi> who, for his plaine dealing paid for all.</p>
            <p n="2">2. This is the Second thing conſiderable: For his diſcourſe tended to this purpoſe: <hi>Aya<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma Horranda:</hi> which is as much as <hi>Honourable</hi> troope of <hi>auditors,</hi> who knowes not but the
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:177839:13"/> God, that made the heauen and earth by his inſtrument, our <hi>Prophet Mahomet,</hi> hath choſen vs of all the nations of the world to be his ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret people, and for this purpoſe raiſed the great <hi>Othoman</hi> to expatiate his power, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>large the <hi>Turkiſh Empire:</hi> For the world had neuer but three true religions, euery one of which had three principall <hi>Prophets:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt God choſe the <hi>Iewes,</hi> and wrought wonders for them in <hi>Aegipt,</hi> and <hi>Canaan</hi> vnder the conduct of that ſame <hi>Prophet Moiſes;</hi> who preſcribed them a law, which had both bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings and curſings, wherein queſtionleſſe, if they had held the beame of integrity vp aright, no doubt he would haue bin as an inpregnable wall of braſſe about them, and terrified their enemies with an hedge of fier; as they vſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt beaſts in the wilderneſſe: but when neither promiſes nor threatnings, bleſſings nor iudgements, proſperity, nor aduerſity, could keepe theſe people cloſe to their maker, but they proued obſtinate and rebellious, yea ſuch refractary delinquents, that they denied their God, and committed Idolatrie in deſpight, and made their ſonns goe through the fier (an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orbitant deuice of the <hi>Deuill:</hi> then God not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:177839:13"/> gaue them ouer to diuers captiuities, but at laſt extirped them and diſſipated them ouer the earth, like chaffe before the winde, ſo that by lamentable experience we ſee, they haue now neither King, nor Preeſt, nor law, nor kingdome, nor gouernment, nor city, nor any countrey of their owne; notwithſtanding God would not be vnfurniſhed of ſeruitors, but pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently raiſed a new <hi>Prophet</hi> who taught the reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion of <hi>Chriſtianity,</hi> and which is a wonder to relate: For all they crucified this good man, &amp; condemned him for a deceiuer of the people, neither taken with the piety of his life, nor ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehending the greatneſſe of his miracles, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther wondring at his perſon, nor admitting of his doctrine, yet after he was dead the very re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port of a few fiſher men, made that impreſſion into the harts of the people, that the mightieſt <hi>Emperors</hi> and kings of the world, <hi>vailed</hi> their <hi>bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nets</hi> to his very title, and laied their crownes downe, to be commanded by his miniſters; But it ſhould ſeeme they grew as corrupt as the <hi>Iewes,</hi> falling into a maine deviſion of their <hi>Church,</hi> with the diſtinction of <hi>Eaſt</hi> and <hi>weſt:</hi> erecting moſt groſely <hi>Idolatry</hi> againe, with ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting vp of images, and a nomber of moſt gew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaw
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:177839:14"/> foppiſh ceremonies, beſides corruption of life and perſonall falts in many impious brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of their law, ſo that God was weary of them to, and not only ſent diviſions amongſt them, but forſooke them in the midſt of their violent race to gormandize and eaſe, laſhing their ſides with the whipps of forraine people, and diſpoſſeſſing them of their chiefeſt cities <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> and <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> to the contriſtation of their hearts, and irrecouerable vexation of their ſoules: yet ſtill is God the gouernour of the world, and prouides himſelfe of another <hi>Prophet</hi> and people, raiſing our great <hi>Mahomet,</hi> &amp; giuing way to our nation to open the ſtore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſe of his wonders to all the world, and to hold the victorie of many nations the ſtronger vnto vs, with an vnvanquiſhable arme, ſo that no doubt we ſhall thriue with a perpetuitie, if we can ſerue this God aright, and take warning by the relapſe of others, not to degenerate from the people of God indeede, but obſerue them with the ſame faith and truſt, as they are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted vnto vs. But alas I tremble to ſpeake it, what haue we done, and what haue we ſeene, wee haue tranſgreſſed in euery point, and from a premeditated wilfulneſse abrogated our firſt
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:177839:14"/> conſtitutions, ſo that God is not only angry, but hath manifeſted it by wonderfull ſignes &amp; tokens, keeping back our <hi>Prophet</hi> from vs, who as you know prefixed a time to returne, with the full conſummation of all happineſſe to his people, ſo that full 40. yeares are elapſed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond his limitation, and our account, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon this fearefull viſion is a prediction of great troubles and alteration:</p>
            <p>For either doth the opening of the booke in the womans hand portend our manifeſt faling away, from the firſt ſcope and intent of our law, whereat as aſhamed the whole armed multitude departed, confounded with the guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tineſſe of their owne conſciences: or elſe it ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifies ſome other booke, in which we haue not yet redd, and againſt which neither force nor pollicy (as it ſhould ſeeme) ſhall preuaile. ſo that to ſpeake with an vndanted confidence of mercy from my God for telling the truth; I am a fraide our religion will be proued adulte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate, &amp; our <hi>Prophet</hi> diſcouered for <hi>Colluſion,</hi> &amp; an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other brought from the touchſtone of truth, for the purer mettaile, &amp; ſo this <hi>Chriſt</hi> that they talke of, ſhall ſhine as glorious as the ſunne &amp; ſet vp his name with euerlaſting eternity.</p>
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:177839:15"/>
            <p>Till this, the company were ſilent, but when they heard him ſo audatious, they cried out vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this blaſphemy, and taking aduantage of their law, which makes all blaſphemy <hi>Capitall,</hi> they preſently condemned him by a definitiue ſentence, and acquainting the <hi>Beglerbeag</hi> with all the occurrences, had both his conſent and warrant to put him to death.</p>
            <p n="3">3. This is the third remarkable thing, which I propoſed, becauſe he died not the ordinary death amongſt them, which is commonly ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to tie about his necke a huge ſtone or pel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let, &amp; ſo caſt him into the ſea; or elſe to ſtrangle him with a ſtring made of ſinues, like our bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtringes, for which executions certaine mutes are alwaies ready, who caſt it ouer his head with a riding knot, and ſo two pulling one way, and two another, quickly thrattle him, &amp; many times with the viole<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce euen ſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der the wine pipe in twaine: but they tooke him by the way of torturing, &amp; ſtriping of him gaue him firſt the <hi>Corbatch,</hi> which was 100. blowes on the ſoles of his feet, with a flat leuer euen to the dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of bloud, the poore man ſtil crying out on the woman that opened the booke. Then they tooke a Bulls pizell, and beat him all ouer to
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:177839:15"/> the cracking of his ſinewes, laſt of all they laid, him vpon a wheele, and with an Indian ſword made of ſinewes halfe an inch thick, a full yard long, a handfull broad, onely it encreaſed to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward the point like a fiſhes taile, brake his bones all to peeces, the Preeſt crying to the laſt gaſp <hi>O thou woman</hi> with the booke ſaue me, and ſo yeelded vp his ſoule, no man knew to whome: nor indeede how to demeane them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues: For the ſame inſtant was a fearefull tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſt, and the <hi>Beglerbeag</hi> by the conſent of the <hi>Muftie</hi> diſpatched certaine of the <hi>Spahies</hi> to the <hi>port</hi> of <hi>Sidon,</hi> that ſo they might acquaint the <hi>Emperor</hi> at <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> with all theſe occurren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces the ſooner.</p>
            <p n="4">4, The Fourth thing conſiderable was the explication of this order of <hi>Deruices,</hi> who are more ſignificantly called <hi>Turners,</hi> they are of the loweſt degree and ſtricteſt order amongſt them, much like our <hi>Capuchines,</hi> they liue in <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templation,</hi> and ſeeme rauiſhed with the appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion of the ioyes of paradiſe. For they preach nothing but abſtinence, and with the <hi>Platoniſt</hi> inferr the immortality of the ſoule: on the daie of ſolemnity, which is our friday, they meete all together in one quadrant, or if you
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:177839:16"/> will ſome <hi>rotunda,</hi> which is gallered round a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout for the people to be ſequeſtred in the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring and viewing their ceremonies, which on this day commonly laſt three houres: the <hi>prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall</hi> of theſe <hi>Preeſts,</hi> all the reſt ſitting croſſe legd in the quadrant, raiſeth vp himſelfe vnto a certaine pulpit, before which, ſuch as haue beene pilgrims at <hi>Mecha</hi> with ſhagg and long haire are ſeated, and on a desk lie their bookes, both of <hi>Perſian</hi> and <hi>Arabian character:</hi> thus ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uanced for the better accommodating his ſpeech to the auditory, he preacheth an hower, and euer as he names the God that giues them bread, a murmuring ſilence much like our cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome at the name of <hi>Ieſu,</hi> is heard amongſt the people with low bending of their bodies, but not a word ſpoken. After his diſcourſe certaine muſick begins, and a ſong of thankſgiuing is diſtinctly pronounced, which finiſhed, the Preeſt, that preacht comes into the quadrant a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the reſt, and leadeth a kinde of mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, with a ſoft and ſober gate; according to the modulent ſound of the muſick, going faſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, and faſter, as the muſique increaſeth, they continuing in the geſture, of looking vp to heauen, and holding vp their hands, till they
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:177839:16"/> turne round as faſt as they can, which laſteth a full quarter of an hower, ſo that either by faint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe or by cuſtome, they fall downe flat vpon the ground, being all in a ſwet, &amp; ſo lie grouel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, til they haue recouered their former breath &amp; ſtrength, certaine officers in the mean while caſting ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tels ouer them, leaſt they catch cold: this turning hath foure diuiſions, and laſteth a full houre, but time ouercommeth all things, and ſo this ſolemnitie receiueth her period, on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the Prieſt, that preacht, returneth backe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine to his pulpit, and after another ſong, bleſſeth the companie, who preſently depart. But you muſt vnderſtand, that no man out of the galleries hath his ſhoes on, nor in any of their <hi>Moſques,</hi> though they paſſe but through. Beſides, they are of great account, and ſome of the fantaſtiques amongſt them, will vndertake to interpret dreames and viſions, and as we ſay, tell fortunes: they commonly diſcouer the ſtrange geſture of naturals and lunaticks, who are vnmocked, vnhurt amongſt the people, and ſo reuerenced with the better ſort, that they verily beleeue ſome inſpiration and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinarie infuſed ſpirit belongs vnto them.</p>
            <pb n="24" facs="tcp:177839:17"/>
            <p>After the Prieſts execution, and that the whole country grew tumultuous through the intricatenes and fearefull diſputing of this Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, my brother and I, to preuent further dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, haſted to <hi>Cayro,</hi> and in good time, as you ſaw, came orderly with the <hi>Carauan,</hi> onely the laſt night there hapned this diſceptation be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene vs: that the opening of the booke in the Viſion muſt needs ſignifie our Bible; to which my haſtines inferred, not by way of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradiction, but by diuerſitie of argument, that then ſurely we doe ill to ſhut the booke, that the people may not read; which my <hi>Auguſtine</hi> brother plainely told mee was ſchiſmaticall. For the booke might be opened to the Clergie, though not to the Laitie: whereupon I repli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, then belike the Laitie muſt know no other, then what we relate vnto them: great reaſon too (ſaid my brother) the letter is death to ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant men, and it is ſufficient for ſuch as re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine in other callings, to vnderſtand no more, then properly belongs to their ſaluation: I ſtill oppoſed, whereby our conference grew to vnkindnes, and ſo reſteth, till a fitter oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunitie for the deciding.</p>
            <p>Well ſaid <hi>Signior Stephano,</hi> agree as well as you
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:177839:17"/> can; but to this I agree, that as I am much a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſed at your diſcourſe, ſo I am reſolued, that this preſageth the conuerſion of the Turks to Chriſtianitie; therefore let vs haſte home into <hi>Italie,</hi> and there we ſhall know what to truſt vnto, or at leaſt both ſecure our ſelues from the confuſions of theſe Kingdomes, and be able to furniſh our vnderſtanding with a better cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taintie of theſe ambiguities. I told them I would accompanie them to <hi>Alexandria,</hi> but I could yet paſſe no further, till I had receiued letters from <hi>Florence</hi> for my diſcharge: and ſo we ordred our affaires accordingly, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming with the ſtreame, tooke the next arme of the riuer, which led vs to the Port.</p>
            <p>But good <hi>Signior,</hi> one noueltie begets ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, at our ſetling our ſelues, we found that the day before, there was arriued the Archbiſhop of <hi>Rhodes,</hi> confined into <hi>Aegypt</hi> by the <hi>Baſhaw,</hi> euen in a manner vpon the like occaſion, as the <hi>Deruice Preist</hi> was executed about <hi>Mecha:</hi> yet there was ſuggeſted againſt him the deliuering of certaine priſoners, whom they call by the name of ſlaues; amongſt whom, diuers Knights of <hi>Malta</hi> ſo ouercame the priuate re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of himſelfe, that in meere commiſeration
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:177839:18"/> and ſome happy remembrance of the place, wherein he liued, he aduentured his owne life for their freedome; all which I learned out of a diſcourſe of his owne, as the Friers brought vs into his preſence, and we gaue attention vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his grauitie and orderly relation of his buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes: but before I enter vpon the particulars of his diſcourſe, I muſt remoue certaine blocks of contradiction, and make my way cleare from abſurditie, and that rough manner of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puting by Queſtions, according to a prouerbe, that a foole may aske a Queſtion, that all the wiſe men in the world cannot reſolue.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Firſt then you muſt know, that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though the Turke haue conquered Greece, and ſome parts of Hungarie, yet he admitteth the toleration of any religion, ſo that they contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute his cuſtomes, and acknowledge his ſupe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rioritie, he is contented to leaue them to their owne eſtabliſhments; ſo that the Greeke Church doe publikely maintaine their ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, and the Roman Catholicks haue by them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues a Church by the name of <hi>Francks,</hi> euen in <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> or if you will, in the <hi>Vines of Pera,</hi> or <hi>Galata,</hi> chuſe you whether: yea when the couetous Patriarcke of <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> would
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:177839:18" rendition="simple:additions"/> haue farmed his place to the Iewes, the Viceer did not permit the ſame, but by way of puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, confinde him to <hi>Zio,</hi> from whence with a beliall ſpirit, he in a monſtrous contumacie went to <hi>Mosko,</hi> and about the yeare 1588. re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned that title to the Archbiſhop there, &amp; for 100000. peeces of gold, inveſted him with the abſolute Primacie of the Patriarck of the Greek Church: but ſee the iuſt iudgment of God, ere he had paſſed quite through <hi>Moldauia,</hi> certaine Ianiſaries ſet vpon him, and not onely tooke away his gold, but bereaued him of his life.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Secondly, you muſt conſider, that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Turkes in taking of priſoners, they haue no diſtinction of perſons, but in their ranſome accounting all ſlaues, and confining them to the Gallies with an ignominious robe, ſhauing them, and marking them on ſome parts of their fleſh.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Thirdly, that this famous towne, and harbour, and Iland of <hi>Rhodes</hi> was remarkable for two things. 1. Firſt, for a <hi>Coloſſus</hi> of braſſe, which boaſted of great antiquitie, and was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed a man in abſolute proportion ſtradling ouer the hauen, betweene whoſe legs, a ſhip with full ſailes, top and top gallant, might en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:177839:19"/> ſo that when the Turke ſurpriſed this place, he laded 1500 Camels with the rubbiſh of this one monument, whereby moſt of his great Ordinance were caſt, which be now in the <hi>Tapinare,</hi> the office of his Artillerie; and whereas you ſhall read that <hi>S. Paul</hi> writ to the <hi>Coloſsians,</hi> it was no other then the inhabitants of <hi>Rhodes.</hi> 2. Secondly, that after the <hi>Knights Templars</hi> were diſſolued, there aroſe a new or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to ſupply that place, called <hi>S. Iohns</hi> of <hi>Ieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem,</hi> who when the Turks conquered Siria and Paleſtina, were of ſo great reuenew in Europe, that for many yeares, they both expulſed the Saracens, and held wars with theſe new Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>humetanes: till at laſt the high decider of controuerſies ſubmitted them to alteration, and both their Monaſterie and their Palace were pulled in peeces, by thoſe barbarous hands, that neither ſpared Ieruſalem, nor the wonderment of the world, the Temple of <hi>Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na</hi> in <hi>Epheſus,</hi> falſified by ſome ſtories vpon <hi>Heroſtratus,</hi> who to perpetuate to himſelfe a name of villanie, ſet it on fire. 4. Laſt of all, that howeuer the Alchoran poſition, of not diſputing of their religion, ſealed vp as it were the lauiſhnes of mens tongues from going at
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:177839:19"/> large, yet will they heare ſtrangers in ciuill op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition, and euen the ſtricteſt arguments, that may conculcate and beat downe their new in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uentions: but this ſeldome happens, becauſe either they learning none but the Perſian or Syriack language, few men vnderſtanding theirs, can diſpute with them.</p>
            <p>But now to the Archbiſhop.</p>
            <p>After the Friers had ouerpaſſed the ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies of gratification, &amp; amplified the diſcourſe of there trauell with the circumſtances of the viſion, the <hi>Archbiſhop</hi> replied: your newes hath no way got any hand of my admiration. For it hath beene long ſince frequent amongſt vs, and vpon another report of the troubles in <hi>Europe,</hi> eſpecially that it rained a whole day bloud into <hi>Tiber,</hi> and that three ſunns were ſeene in full radiance ouer the citie of <hi>Rome,</hi> ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny <hi>Greeke preeſts</hi> reſorted vnto me to <hi>Rhodes</hi> with an impreſſed cheerefulneſſe, as if our <hi>Church</hi> were already re-eſtabliſhed in the firſt forme of the primitiue patterne: nor paſſed it thus amongſt our ſelues; but the <hi>Baſhaw</hi> ſent for me in all haſt, and not only demanded my opinion of theſe things, but made meanes to certaine doctors of their law to enter into fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:177839:20"/> diſputation with me, I told them plainely, that the originall of <hi>Mahomet</hi> was a meere de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſe, which they might eaſily perceiue by the aſſotiation of <hi>Sergius</hi> one of our moncks. For if he had beene a <hi>Prophet</hi> of God, he would que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtionleſse neuer haue intermingled any deui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of man: then againe for his prefixed time of returning, it was a thing neuer heard nor red of, that any one returned from the dead, nor ſhall euer riſe, till the laſt diſsolution, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore how much are you beholding to that God which you doe now worſhip, that hath from heauen diſcouered vnto you in a viſion what you muſt truſt vnto in theſe latter times, &amp; if you be not ſtupified with obſtinacy, &amp; remain more ſtony hearted then euer the <hi>Iewes</hi> were, that crucified the Sauiour of the world, now are glad tidings brought vnto you: For the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, which appeared is queſtionleſſe the Church of God compaſsed about with a <hi>Sunne,</hi> repreſenting the ſonne of righteouſneſse, euen <hi>Chriſt</hi> the Sauiour of mankind, without whom no fleſh can come to happineſse; the booke in her hand is queſtionleſſe the ſcriptures, and the opening of it, prefigureth the ſearching and contemplation of the ſecrets: but whereas ſo
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:177839:20"/> great an army ſtil fled, as ſhe opened the booke, how can any thing be perſonated by it, but that both <hi>Perſians, Moores,</hi> and your ſelues, will be aſhamed and abaſhed to conceiue in what a ſottiſh ignorance and ſenceleſs blindneſse, you haue beene ſo many yeares detained, therefore embrace the truth, and returne to <hi>Chriſtianity,</hi> which will bring you into the direct path of ſaluation, and in the end the glorious king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of heauen. Why replied one of the <hi>Doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Iewiſh Doctors.</note> how can this be? your prophet was but a man, as ours was, and for inuentions of men your religion exceeds, and farre exceedes thoſe <hi>fanaticall</hi> impoſitions, as you terme them that euer <hi>Mahomet</hi> gaue vs.</p>
            <p>But among all as the <hi>Iewes</hi> haue often told you, there be three or foure ſuch ſtrange things in your religion, that it is impoſſible for an ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt reſolution to apprehend, that God would be ſerued ſo foppiſhly, and childiſhly: Firſt the erecting of Images: did God caſt away the <hi>Iewes,</hi> &amp; as I haue heard, curſed <hi>Ieroboams</hi> calues, yea rent the kingdome from your great <hi>Salo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon,</hi> and all becauſe he gaue way to the <hi>Idols</hi> of his wiues, and will you haue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs be ſo entangled againe, as to heap vp vengeance for ſo foule
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:177839:21"/> an abſurdidie on our owne heads? Beleeue it, it will neuer be and it is impoſſible.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Secondly your prophanation of the <hi>Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>both.</hi> Doe we or the <hi>Iewes</hi> buy and ſell as you doe? labour and trauell, eat and gurmandize, gamboll and play, dance, and ſing and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit ſuch abuſes on that day, as if all the weeke were tied into one bundell, and then ſet open to floriſh her expences.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Thirdly your diſpenſations with ſinne and ſelling of indulgences for mony: O God! is God a receiuer of money? or what conceit haue you to thinke, that he that is all loue and mercy, will be corrupted with reward, or brought about with mercenary bribes?</p>
            <p n="4">4. Laſt of all your ſumptuous liues, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe of vanity, wherein your <hi>Cardinals</hi> goe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond greater princes, and ſhame indeede their profeſſion with vnſanctified ſuperfluitie: I name no more becauſe, I know theſe be vn an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerable and not capable of the diſtinction of perſonall falts.</p>
            <p>With that I replied, although theſe might be all well excuſed with circumſtantiall infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and apologicall inferences, that the maine points of ſaluations are held amongſt them,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:177839:21"/> yet you know, we haue oppoſed <hi>Rome</hi> in theſe things, and not only returned the pride of their ſupremacy vpon their heads, but diſcouered their tirannous vſurpation of our rights. For Chriſtianity began in <hi>Antioche</hi> and the <hi>Greekes</hi> were the firſt receiuers of the truth, long before the <hi>Latines,</hi> therefore belieue it without fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther diſputing, vnleſs we had time to ouer look <hi>Ptolemeis</hi> library of 200000. bookes, both <hi>Rome</hi> ſhall be diſrobed, <hi>Antichriſt</hi> diſcouered, &amp; the riuer of <hi>Tiber</hi> flow with bloud, as this the rayning of bloud prefigureth, and <hi>Mahometh</hi> himſelfe proued an impoſtor, ſo that both <hi>Iewes</hi> and <hi>Turks</hi> doe what you can, and ſay what you liſt, ſhall be taken into our fold, and ſet downe in the accounts of Gods ſheepe, and the <hi>Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an flock of Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When I had made an end of my ſpeech, I proteſt I cannot tell; whether I left them to the extremity of rage or laughter: For they were ſo farr from approouing my words, that they cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed out it was pitty ſuch a fellow ſhould liue, &amp; ſo the <hi>Baſhaw</hi> to ſhew himſelfe a true maintai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of the <hi>Othoman</hi> glory, committed me to pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, where I remained, vntill ſuch time as their came a new enforcement againſt me, for hid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:177839:22"/> out of the way certaine knights of <hi>Malta,</hi> ſlaues, and taken by their gallies in a florentine ſhip as ſuppoſed to ioyne with the pyrates, that had proiected the ſurpriſing of <hi>Scanderon:</hi> but the <hi>Baſhaw</hi> willing to ſaue my life, as much af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecting theſe gray haires, my former demea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor, and that outward proportion I carry, ſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped me from <hi>Rhodes</hi> to <hi>Alex:</hi> and hath confined me an exile to <hi>Aegipt,</hi> with licence to liue in <hi>Cayro</hi> as I liſt.</p>
            <p>Hence aroſe a new contention betweene the Friers and himſelfe, about the Popes ſuprema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, &amp; the augmentation of the Clergies pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er from the donation of Princes, and the ſuffra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of generall Councels, but the Archbiſhop quickly cut them of, and told them plainely, that the Italian Biſhop was but an vſurper, and he made no doubt but the raining of bloud in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Tyber prefigured the deſtruction of Rome, &amp; the ſhining of the Sunns an hereafter mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtation of greater truth: For fellowes, ſaith he, you know, that our <hi>Iohn, Patriarch</hi> of <hi>Conſtantino<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple</hi> beganne theſe tumors of ambition, againſt whom your Biſhop of Rome, called the Great <hi>Gregorie</hi> oppoſed, aſsuring him that any aſſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of ſuch an vniuerſal title was antichriſtian
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:177839:22"/> but what followed: the deſtruction of Phocas and Mauritius the Emperors of the Eaſt, and the horrible combination of Bonifacius in the Weſt, which your Biſhops can relate, as for your <hi>Arrian</hi> faction; what a wonder was ſhown in the world, when our poore <hi>Athanaſius</hi> for op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing 700. Biſhops, was condemned for an Heretick, had not our bleſſed Emperor inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicted the ſentence, and ſauing him, by a viſion ſent for him to priuate conference, wherein the ſpirit made him ſo great a workmaſter, that he confirmed the Emperor in his faith, and made that Creed, which is ſo famous, for the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſion of <hi>Europe:</hi> as for your Images, who knowes not, that the Councells of Nice, and Conſtance were contradictory about it, and at laſt a ſentence preuailed for their ouerthrow, and ſo could I proceed to the ouerthrow of the reſt, but that I will haue no further wrangling, therefore haſt you into Italie and mark but the reuolution of times, and what I by way of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction haue ſpoken: For on my ſoule both <hi>Iewes</hi> and <hi>Turks</hi> ſhall turne to Chriſtianitie, and Rome your babiloniſh Rome, ſhall beſet on fire, to the terror of all the world, that haue wiſhed well to the great ſtrumpet, who hath
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:177839:23"/> made the Kings of the earth drunke with the cup of her abomination. With this the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany deuided themſelues. The Arch-Biſhop prepared for <hi>Cayro:</hi> the Friers and the reſt for <hi>Florence,</hi> and I ſetled awhile in <hi>Alexandria,</hi> from whence hauing ſo conuenient a meſſenger I thought it my dutie to acquaint you with theſe occurrences, wherein if I haue ſomewhat ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended the limits of a letter, I craue your par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don and hope you will conceiue, that my good will ouercame diſcretion; and ſo I commit my ſelfe to your care for my diſpach, and in all hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militie. <hi>Baſcio le honorate mani di V. S.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <date>
                  <hi>Octob:</hi> 12. 1619. <hi>Stilo nouo.</hi>
               </date>
               <signed>Oſſeruantiſsimo: Ludouico Cortano. </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="translators_epilogue">
            <pb n="37" facs="tcp:177839:23"/>
            <head>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> 
               <hi>The Tranſlators Epilogue.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>WHat I haue done, you now both ſee &amp; read. For it cannot be recalled, nor do I meane to make any apology, though it be but like a ſpiders cobweb, fit for nothing but ſweeping away, leaſt I proue like the cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tier, that leaped reaſonable well vpon the ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daine taking him in his bootes, but when he thought to put them of, and make apparent his further dexterity and ſtrength, he came far ſhort, and thus you ſhall read of Protogenes pencell, that hauing made an arteficiall dogge and comming to finiſh it, with the muzſled haire about his chaps, he ſtill miſliked it, and wiped it away, till at laſt caſting his pencell from him in a rage, he effected that by chance, which all his art was defectiue in: For applica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion I haue now done a thing as we ſay, <hi>ex im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prouiſo,</hi> not caring to what vſe the reader puts it to, ſo I haue my owne ends: yet as I heare, it will be likt, whether I will or no, and is meerely a tricke of blind fortune to out-face both good endeauours, and true ſcholerſhip: For let me neuer be truſted, if euer ſo hood-winckt a
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:177839:24"/> bayard aduentured before on ſo hard a ſtile, and durſt publiſh it as a worke, either wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy the viewing, or cenſuring. The obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate Papiſt will ſtorme, and the pedanticall humoriſt will ſweare, if not ſweat: the cenſorious traueller will ſmile, the noueliſt will buy it, though it were a lye; and he that liues by an Almanack will ſuppoſe, there may be ſomething in it for direction; the yong man may affect it, being himſelfe not ſolid enough for a Critick; and ſome old men may be yong enough to entertaine it: The free-hearted Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman will ſay, it was well done to affright idlenes with ſome endeuors; and the man of grauitie and learning will conclude it a deuiſe to get money. To get money; what as this world goes? In the name of Couetouſnes, who would care for money? when euery mans dores are open to the hungry belly, euery na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked ſoule clothed, euery empty purſe filled, nay a man cannot looke ſadly, but his friend will aske him, what he ayleth; and if want be the cauſe, ſend him a gratuitie the next morning; when our yong Ladies will leaue off their tiers, painting, and fethers to beſtow it on poore Schollers, and a man ſhall no ſooner character
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:177839:24"/> a booke with a <hi>Moecenas,</hi> but the Lord will ſend all ouer the towne to looke him out, and not trouble him to waite vpon him: when the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney ſhall be ſpared, that was wont to be ſpent vpon Barbers, panders, and whores, and equal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly diuided amongſt men of well-deſeruing. In a word, when olde acquaintance will ſtay his Caroch in the ſtreets to ſpeake to his decayed frend; and when he comes home to negotiate with him, will ſend for him vp without excu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, though he be in bed with his Lady. Not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding all this, conſidering my diſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrous improuidence, and dogged humor to ſnarle at the baſenes of men indeed; I was glad it got money: For if the worſt fall; I ſhall be able while it laſt to pay for my dinner, and preuent the cutting my throat, in expecting to be ſent for elſe-where: yet good Reader, in way of ciuilitie, I would it could get you ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what too; that is, if you cannot beleeue it as truth, yet to make that vſe of it, as if it were true; and then ſhall you know, there is but one way to happines, and all the praedictions, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſies, viſions, apparitions, Comets, invnda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, ſtormes, tempeſts, famine, warre, altera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:177839:25" rendition="simple:additions"/> and ſubuerſion of Kingdomes, with all the cabinet of of myſteries, tend to this end, that proemium and <hi>poena</hi> be the maſtring curbs of the world: that is, that God hath a <hi>Magazin</hi> of iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to inflict on the obſtinate ſinner with puniſhments; and a ſtore-houſe of mercy to ſupport the penitent ſoule with comfort.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
